Daniel Lemire Computer scientist

lemire@gmail.com • ca.linkedin.com/in/dlemire/ • github.com/lemire/

Montreal, Canada • Canadian Citizen • Father of two clever boys

Summary

I have been an entrepreneur, a government researcher and a university professor. I have been programming sofware since I was 12 years old and I never stopped. My contributions appear in several open-source projects: Git, Apache Hive, Apache Spark, Apache Lucene, Netflix Atlas, LinkedIn Pinot, Elastic, TensorFlow, Apache Kylin, Druid. I am a beneficiary of the Google Open Source Peer Bonus Program.

Writing (with collaborators)

- I have written over 45 refereed publications and I have been cited thousands of times.
- My blog has been featured on Reddit, Hacker News and Slashdot.

Software (with collaborators)

Roaring bitmap Fast bitmaps used by Apache Spark • Apache Kylin • Druid • Lucene, Solr, Elastic

JavaFastPFOR Fast integer compression used by Lucene 4.x

EWAH Fast bitmaps used by Apache Hive • Git

Recent experience

LICEF Research Center • TELUQ, Université du Québec

Montreal, Canada

Computer Science Professor

2004-

Promoted to full professor early (2009). Funded by NSERC Discovery grants (2003-2007, 2007-2012, 2012-2017) in computer science. Program committee member at major conferences (ACM SIGIR, ACM CIKM, ACM WSDM, ACM RecSys).

National Research Council of Canada

Canada

Research Officer 2002–2004

Founded and lead the e-Health research group. Designed the Slope One algorithm.

Education

Ecole Polytechnique • Université de Montréal

Montréal, Canada

Ph.D. in Engineering Mathematics (graduated in 2 $\frac{1}{2}$ years)

1998

University of Toronto

TORONTO, CANADA

B.Sc. and M.Sc. (very high distinction, master completed in one year)

1994, 1995

Skills

Can program productively in Java, C++, C, Python, Go, Swift, JavaScript

Fluent in French (mother tongue), English (full professional proficiency).